okay let's try a particularly difficult
one today I feel like trying to make a
bigger move Lucic to say to do something
which requires already having a couple
of the other concepts in place so today
I will be importing concepts of the
complicated the complex that's episode 2
and to a lesser extent some of the other
concepts that you can find in my
immediate posts I'll try to keep that
relatively light but if you haven't
really read and understood the concepts
the complicated complex and the kinetic
model you might want to do that first so
we'll be talking about today is
something that I referred to as the
Tainter plus model this is a extension
or an effort to be an extension of the
model that was put forward by Joseph
Tainter I should point out that painter
has no idea what I'm doing here and so
this is not something that he has any
particular endorsement of so by ordinary
deep code rules if any of this sounds
good or interesting then you should have
seen this entire the kids and it sounds
bad foolish you should assume that it's
entirely minor or ours all right so with
that caveat this idea requires a little
bit of exposition so it might take
longer than usual I hope you bear with
me but I do actually think it's more the
more interesting and incisive concepts
that's out there it begins with the
observation of the fact that the way we
humans so far in civilization typically
get what we need from the complex
natural world which is to say the way
that we access and make use of resources
of complex nature is that we innovate
construct and manage complicated
structures to do it and we might say
that the the Tainter plus model is an
observation
how this dynamic seems to continually
play out I'm going to use a particular
metaphor throughout the conversation
which is the oil system the oil industry
of the oil economy excetera is an
example of a complicated system and oil
in this case being a complex natural
resource so it begins with the discovery
of a possibility of an opportunity you
already have some kind of social
environment that is more or less getting
its needs met and you come across some
capability of accessing some useful
resource that can add value to your
social environment so it is discovered
that oil can be used safe for example
for energy I'm going to simplify the
example arrived I know that petroleum
has lots and lots of different uses and
I don't know the exact history perfectly
so let's just imagine that it's a route
of origin the story starts with energy
in the beginning you don't really need
it anywhere you've already got the
energy sources that you need your
society it's not built around access to
the meat and well just discover people
to do that so it's all upside and in
fact it's generally almost by definition
relatively easy to cat because otherwise
you didn't spend any time looking for
it's not something that's currently
deeply deeply valuable so let's say you
can go out with a shovel to some fields
and dig up some sand and through some
relatively simple process have yourself
a barrel of oil and then you can use it
for running lamps or lubricating axles
or whatnot and the energy return is
quite substantial compared to the energy
investment let's say maybe you get a
hundred barrels of oil of useful value
for the equivalent of one barrel of oil
of energy expended because there's just
a lot of low-hanging fruit this space of
resource has not been yet meaningfully
explored and for some reason you've
entered into the possibility of getting
there and so it began
what happens here is that because the
the resource shows up is that not being
useful and in fact because of the ratio
between energy expenditure net returned
it shows it as being attractive more
people begin to spend more time getting
it using it and as a consequence it
begins to add value to the social
infrastructure the possibilities become
actualities and it becomes useful and
interesting to build more things on this
foundation you might for example begin
to innovate things that require the use
of oil so you debate the internal
combustion engine and this gives rise to
airplanes and to shifting farmers
feeding double oil or to a motive
industries I'm in a fashion if stiff the
wooden existed before and so on the one
hand you see is an expansion of social
capability not on the basis of this new
bathing's new reservoir of potential on
the other hand what you begin to see
also is that the low-hanging fruit get
picked relatively quickly and you find
it becomes a little bit harder to access
the underlying resource so now instead
of being able to just kind of dig it up
with a shovel you have to actually build
some kind of structure and maybe because
it's being used more broadly you also
have to build ways of distributing it
more broadly and perhaps if the use
cases are in fact more diverse gifted
actually start in certain processing
mechanisms to pull out the distillates
and to convert into plastics and whatnot
and so it as if happening is in order to
take advantage of the increasing
possibilities in order to maintain an
increasing demand you have to increase
your intensity of extraction what is
becoming a more challenging to extract
process and distribute resource which
means you end up having to build a more
complicated structure to do all this
work that's the major move
and there are a couple of consequences
to this one which I think it's important
to note up front is that as far as I can
tell any interaction of the complicated
of the complex will result in some
externality to the complex some waste
product or some disruption to the
homeostatic feedback loops that maintain
the integrity to complex system so in
this case for example and the minimum
you are going to be destroying the
physical environment where you're
extracting oil and at least in the
narrowband air like the ground is no
longer what it used to be and of course
you see broader consequences at the
outside the use of the resources out
putting carbon into the atmosphere
throughout the distribution channel you
have opportunities for you know take oil
tankers spin etc and I should mention by
the way you also have different outputs
in different layers the four layer model
you might for example find yourself and
the odd circumstance that you're having
to maintain a military structure to hold
politically aligned regimes and
locations that have access to this
resource which means you're actually
creating extra Nelly's into your social
complex environment and not just in the
physical later so one is this this
output of externalities from complicated
into complex in a fashion that begins to
break down the home aesthetic capacity
of the complex environment the second
observation is that the complicated
institutions need you're putting
together have an increasing carrying
cost whether they're there some a real
thing and they have a lot of maintenance
involved you can imagine that you have
to be able to build an entire
manufacturing industry to curriculum
equipment to create the underlying
structures to extract me well you have
to build a transportation industry to be
able to move in from point OnBeat you
have to train people to be able to
operate this stuff in at a certain point
of time you get a whole lot of carrying
cost
so then we get to the the next move
would be the ratio of energy returned
for an energy expended goes through a
curve in the beginning you'll see a
situation where the ability to get
better at doing it pays dividends and so
as you're becoming more complicated
you're actually also becoming more
efficient so maybe ratio goes from one
pair with ten barrels of energy returned
from one barrel energy expended to a
hundred to one because you just kind of
pick the low-hanging fruit in what you
might call innovation space not the
low-hanging fruit and just finding the
oil but the low-hanging fruit and
getting better at finding the oil and
this is the classic acceleration part of
an innovation s-curve and so this has by
the way the consequence of making you
want to double down if you're actually
getting better and better better so keep
doing it extend up until you build out
but at a certain point there's going to
be a tipping point where the low-hanging
fruit in innovation space and sound
start to get harder to get and so you're
now spending more and more to get the
same amount or even a declining amount
of innovation which is still shown
represent as an acceleration in the
underlying return on physical oil so if
he used to spend a dollar to get ten
dollars of oil and now you're spending a
dollar to get this is very complicated
you're spending a barrel of oil to get
innovation that say increases your rate
of return on an energy investment in oil
by 10% and then in the next year it only
increases your rate of return in oil by
8% cease your acceleration is decelerate
but the velocity is still increasing but
now it's happening is you're getting
into the middle of that S curve which
means the top is coming but at the same
time you're now stuck in this situation
where your social infrastructure is now
deeply committed to this underlying
resource and into the
proliferated almost like the way the
roots that can increasingly complicated
as they expand out the proliferating
news cases and the entire social
environment so now you have not just a
useful resource for transportation you
have an entire transportation sector
trucking and trains and automotive that
has people using oil for tires and for
duplication and you know a giant
fraction of the entire employment base
is built on top of the foundation of
this resource and its production its
processing this distribution it's used
so it hasn't happened as you find
yourself in the situation where on the
one hand isn't gigantic complicated
infrastructure she's not proliferating
throughout the entire social field got
political influence you've got academic
and scientific is becoming too big to
fail yet on the other hand precisely
because it's becoming increasingly
complicated and it's carrying cost is
becoming higher and higher and more and
more fragile it's actually becoming well
right now fertile as it as a whole
system so we have known a some kind of
relationship between the growth of the
underlying extracted and used capability
and externalities from the complicated
in the complex you have a increasing
difficulty in actually access and first
innovation and then second the actual
underlying resource so your energy
investment to energy return ratio is
beginning to slow down you've got an
increasing requirement or dependence of
the overall social environment on this
complicated institution and you have an
increasing complicatedness carrying cost
and fragility in by the way difficulty
and modified the central islands to to
she so like that last is important the
difficulty modifying means things like
it's actually really not at all simple
to migrate a vast oil infrastructure to
some other kind of infrastructure it
seems like I might
to move from say oil to solar electric
even if you're doing it very
deliberately it's not and obviously
there's lots of things that can't you
actually need still they don't have to
do stuff that solar can't do okay and by
the way all of this and this is kind of
the point is so massively complicated to
do way outside of the the conscious
awareness of the collective intelligence
that is driving and making decisions in
the environment so this is all stuff
that's being done kind of in the
unconscious intelligence that happens in
just markets it's outside of the scope
of any truly comprehensive systems
consciousness it's happening almost
instinctively at this point so then you
get to the last level at some point
somewhere something breaks either the
energy invested to energy return it
starts to vector towards flat meaning
you're putting a barrel oil in and
you're only getting unbearable out in
fact maybe you start getting less than a
barrel of oil out and you're actually
burning other resources to maintain this
thing and by the way think about this in
the context of the four layer model it
might be that you're burning cultural or
social resources or geopolitical
resources or you're falsifying financial
records to maintain the integrity of
something over here that's happening in
the energy space but these things can
actually be transformed back and forth
it's really easy to lose track of what's
going on when you make those
transformations if you're subsidizing
energy through military it may be
difficult to connect the dots in any
event the net-net
energy expended begins to actually be
more than energy returned and now you're
you're screwed at some point this is
going to come to an end
or maybe the complex system begins to
break down
you've been powering massive kinds of
externalities from the complicated very
complex environment something Lambrecht
and again this is something might be
something simple like you just could
have reached the edge of the ability to
reach the resource your innovations
passages can't jump some gap in here
no longer able to get you hunted the
prey animal to extinction and just
there's no more prey animals or again
maybe if it finds it's going to some
other domain it's not obvious to make
the connection so climate change is so
you can obviously example here but again
economics and politics are equal
equivalent or the complicated system
itself begins to have so much can it
becomes rokuko'
becomes nearly impossible to stay ahead
of the Red Queen's race that you're
running faster and faster and faster you
just to stay even and you're gonna spin
plates just just can't keep keeping pace
things are beginning to become so
fragile that cascades and breakdowns
bring the whole thing down and you know
that that's that you find yourself in a
situation where you cannot continue
going down this path and yet you have
now become really rather deeply addicted
to this path and so any negative any
slowdown even not even going back or
just decrease in velocity starts to show
up as some kind of crisis this is the
last movement of the Taylor curve so
your innovation curve is now to this but
the Tainter curve is now about to do
this and you end up with some kind of
involuntary collapse in the kinetic
model and Snowden you are now moving
from the complicated environment into
some kind of dive through chaos and
unfortunately the further down the taint
occurred God the more broke a code
you're complicated institutions the more
deeply connected this particular
structure it is to the rest of the
social system the more likely that you
waited too long and therefore the more
likely your dive through chaos is going
to be rather deep
okay and that's that's that some things
to keep in mind obviously I've mentioned
innovation and this this model actually
includes when innovation itself shows up
and the fact that innovation has its own
decreasing returns in particular domains
what's interesting about this is that it
actually is domain specific that once
you've created a bounded complicated
domain the complicated is by definition
finite and bounded while you may have a
large amount of territory to explore
then the less that territory is finite
and this is one of the primary reasons
why you get decreasing returns to
innovation
you are not innovating in the total
space of possible invention you're
innovating the space of getting better
at deep pulling this resource in this
case oil which means you're gonna have
some innovation s-curve and all your
novel innovations anything new that you
might explore are going to show up as
like choices that you can't make they're
going to show this solar in 1973 they're
going to show up as you know maybe
stopping engaging in energy consumption
at this level and for other reasons
where they're going to see things there
in the sort of the possibilities space
of invention but not in the possibility
space using adventure for the purposes
of explorers to me
so that's crucial and all of this is not
taking place in the context of this
relationship between a complicated in
the complex and while it does very much
seem to be the case that this Tainter
plus model describes something
fundamental which is that if you're
playing the game of taking complicated
to act on and extract what you need from
the complex you're in a tainted process
and by the way you are also the Snowden
process this does not necessarily mean
that we humans are forever committed to
writing this cycle of discovered new
possibility become addicted to it and
then collapse what it means is that we
may need to figure out how to do things
that are more fluidly fundamentally
connected to the complex which to say
right in the complex do things in the
complicated but never find ourselves
addicted to and committed to the
complicated that is part of the path of
what do good choices look like how do we
figure this thing out that this model
gives rise to all right I think that's
plenty and I hope that this landed